

🛘 (+47) 411 42 466 | 🗷 erik@i-solution.de | Rº Erik Kusch | 🕲 0000-0002-4984-7646 | 🎢 erikkusch.com | 🖫 ErikKusch | 💆 KuschErik

Research Profile

I am a biostatistican and data scientist specialised in streamlining work-flows as well as integrating and analysing heterogeneous data products. I use and develop quantitative tools to study the impacts of climate change and investigate the resilience of system at macro-scales to understand trajectories through time and space. My current work includes software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation as well as inference, analysis, and simulation of ecological networks.

Education

PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics, Data Analysis and Biodiversity

01/2020 - 04/2023

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

Dissertation: A Macroecological Perspective to Ecological Networks - Exploring the Impacts of Climate-Driven Biodiversity

Change & Contrasting and Benchmarking Network Inference Approaches

M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

University of Bergen (UIB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

Thesis: Inferring Vegetation Memory From Remote Sensing Data And Identifying Causal Links To Plant Function

B.Sc. in Biology 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

Specialised Training

Invasive Species Monitoring with Remote Sensing

NASA'S APPLIED REMOTE SENSING TRAINING (ARSET) 11/08/2024 - 28/08/2024

Open, Reproducible, and Transparent Science in Ecology Finse, Norway

University of Bergen 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats 26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics Glasgow, Scotland

University of Glasgow 06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities with the R-package Hmsc Helsinki, Finland

UNIVERSITY OF HELSINKI 02/11/2020 - 06/11/2020

Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems Hamburg, Germany

University of Hamburg 23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

Experience

Advisor Oslo, Norway

CICERO Center for International Climate Research 09/2024 - PRESENT

Senior Engineer / Research Infrastructure Manager
Oslo, Norway

Natural History Museum, University of Oslo 03/2023 - 12/2024

Visiting Researcher Onna, Japan

OKINAWA INSTITUTE FOR SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY 02/2024 - 12/2024

Research FellowBergen, Norway

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN 09/2019 - 12/2019

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide

Saxony, Germany

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS 04/2016 - 06/2016

Research and Teaching Assistant

Behavioural Ecology Research Group, University of Leipzig 08/2017 - 08/2019: 03/2017 - 04/2017

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO 07/2018

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP 05/2017 - 07/2017

NFDI4Biodiversity & iDiv Seasonal School on Data Management in Biodiversity and Environmental Science	Q Course Materia
Author & Lecturer	
Bayesian Networks Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
uthor & Lecturer	
AU Bayes Study Group	🔇 Personal Course Web Page
uthor & Lecturer	
xcursions into Biostatistics	🔇 Course Web Page
uthor & Lecturer	
n Introduction to Biostatistics Using R	😯 Course Web Page
uthor & Lecturer	
iological Research in Theory and Praxis (BFTP)	Course Web Page
UTHOR	Aarhus Universit
eaching Assistant	Aarhus Universit
PPLIED STATISTICS	22/03/2021 - 14/05/202
ratistical and Geospatial Modelling	03/09/2020 - 18/12/202
EOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS	27/10/2020 - 18/12/202
nstructor & Advisor	
COINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS), AARHUS UNIVERSITY	03/02/2021 - 05/05/202
ENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN	08/2017 - 07/201
lonours & Grants & Awards	
cholarships & Grants	
$10/2020 \textbf{Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students}, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ France Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, \ France Christian Frantsen's Scholarship for Academical Frantsen's Scholarshi$	p Aarhus, Denmark
03/2019 Funding for Particularly Talented Students , Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norwa
02/2019 Fast-Track-Initiative Funding , FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norwa
03/2018 Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norwa
2018/19 Scholarship , German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen V	olkes) Bonn, German
WARDS	
10/2019 Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher , International Society for Ecological M	odelling Salzburg, Austria
10/2019 Modeller's Choice Poster Award, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austri
xtracurricular Activity	
roup Leader	
oders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo	08/2023 - 12/202
atural History Museum Computational Biology Help-desk, University of Oslo	08/2023 - 12/202
aturviterne Union Representative	, , , , ,
NIVERSITY OF OSLO NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM	07/2023 - 12/202
vous Mossbox	, , , ,
roup Member	00/2022 DDESEN

Leader & Dungeon MasterCICERO DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP12/2023 - PRESENTUNIVERSITY OF OSLO NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP05/2023 - 12/2024AARHUS UNIVERSITY SECTION FOR ECOINFORMATICS DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP03/2022 - 01/2023

08/2023 - PRESENT

03/2021 - 03/2023 03/2021 - 03/2023

09/2018 - 12/2019

STADIS - STABILITY AND DISCONTINUITY GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO

STATISTICS JOURNAL CLUB, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW

Bayes Study Group, University of Bergen

SPATIAL SHARED-INTEREST GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW

Writing

Fragmented Networks: Challenges in communication and cohesion of European Biodiversity Research Infrastructures

Tomáš Martinovič, Allan T. Souza, Carrie Andrew, Yi-Ming Gan, Erik Kusch

6 Biodiversity Data Journal - 2024

Naturally formed canopy gaps increase tree species diversity in the tropical Moist Afromontane Forest of Gerba Dima, southwest Ethiopia

BEDILU TAFESSE, ERIK KUSCH, TAMRAT BEKELE, SEBESBE DEMISSEW, BIKILA WARKINEH, DESALEGN CHALA

TwinEco: A Unified Framework for Dynamic Data-Driven Digital Twins in Ecology

TAIMUR KHAN, KOEN DE KONING, DAG ENDRESEN, DESALEGN CHALA, ERIK KUSCH

Rx Preprint - 2024

Prototype biodiversity digital twin: crop wild relatives genetic resources for food security

DESALEGN CHALA, ERIK KUSCH, CLAUS WEILAND, CARRIE ANDREW, JONAS GRIEB, TUOMAS ROSSI, TOMAS MARTINOVIC, DAG ENDRESEN

Plant trait and vegetation data along a 1314 m elevation gradient with fire history in Puna grasslands, Perú

AUD HALBRITTER, VIGDIS VANDVIK, SEHOYA COTNER, [...], ERIK KUSCH, [...], BRIAN ENQUIST

Mature Scientific Data - 2024

A Novel Simulation Framework for Validation of Ecological Network Inference

ERIK KUSCH*, ANNA C. VINTON* (* ... JOINT FIRST-AUTHORSHIP)

Rx Preprint - 2023

Ecological Network Resilience & Extinction Proxies - Updating Projections of Ecological Networks

ERIK KUSCH, ALEJANDRO ORDONEZ

Rx Preprint - 2023

Ecological Network Inference is not Consistent Across Scales or Approaches

ERIK KUSCH, MALYON BIMLER, JAMES A. LUTZ, ALEJANDRO ORDONEZ

Rx Preprint - 2023

NetworkExtinction - R Package to Simulate Extinction Propagation & Rewiring Potential in Ecological Networks

 $\texttt{M.Isidora\, \'Avila-Thieme}^\star, \textbf{Erik\, Kusch}^\star, \texttt{Derek\, Corcoran}^\star, ..., \texttt{Navarrete}, \texttt{Pablo\, A.\, Marquet\, (}^\star \, ... \, \texttt{Joint\, first-authorship})$

Methods in Ecology and Evolution - 2023

MOSAIC: A Unified Trait Database to Complement Structured Population Models

Connor Bernard, Gabriel Silva Santos, [...], \mathbf{Erik} \mathbf{Kusch} , [...], $\mathbf{Roberto}$ Salguero-Gómez

• Nature Scientific Data - 2023

A novel trophic cascade between cougars and feral donkeys shapes desert wetlands

 ${\sf Erick \, Lundgren, \, Daniel \, Ramp, \, Owen \, Middleton, \, Eamonn \, Wooster, \, \textbf{Erik \, Kusch}, \, [...], \, Arian \, Wallach}$

■ Journal of Animal Ecology - 2022

Vegetation memory effects and their association with vegetation resilience in global drylands

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY, ALISTAIR SEDDON

■ Journal of Ecology - 2022

KrigR - A Tool for Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY

• Environmental Research Letters - 2022

Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR

RICHARD DAVY, ERIK KUSCH

Environmental Research Letters - 2021